<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the right reuerend and right honorable the Lords spirituall and temporall assembled in vpper House of this most high and honorable session of Parliament an abstract of the grieuances and oppressions done by Sir Arthur Ingram, Knight, and his agents, to Griswell Rogers, widow, and her poore orphan.</title>
            <author>Rogers, Griswell.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10905</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21176.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3369</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33143376</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33143376</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28428</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10905)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28428)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1885:55)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the right reuerend and right honorable the Lords spirituall and temporall assembled in vpper House of this most high and honorable session of Parliament an abstract of the grieuances and oppressions done by Sir Arthur Ingram, Knight, and his agents, to Griswell Rogers, widow, and her poore orphan.</title>
                  <author>Rogers, Griswell.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: faded, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rogers, Griswell --  Estate.</term>
               <term>Ingram, Arthur, --  Sir, d. 1642.</term>
               <term>Copyhold.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="abstract">
            <pb facs="tcp:28428:1"/>
            <head>To the right Reuerend and right Honorable the Lords ſpirituall and temporall
aſſembled in the vpper Houſe of this moſt high and honorable Seſſion of Parliament. An Abſtract of the grieuances and oppreſſions done by Sir Arthur Ingram Knight and his agents,
to Griſwell Rogers widow and her poore Orphans.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Griſwell Rogers her title,</head>
               <p>Moſt humbly ſheweth,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heygrane</hi> in <hi>Somerſet,</hi> with all the lands therein, parcell of the ioynture of the Ladie <hi>Iane</hi> late Queene of <hi>England,</hi> of 5 <abbr>l.</abbr> 9 <hi>
                     <abbr>s.</abbr> 
                     <hi>per annum</hi>
                  </hi> Rent were
granted to <hi>Beſt</hi> and <hi>Britton, 44. Eliz.</hi> by Letters pattents vnder the great Seale, which lands (by conveyances) are ſince come to the hands of <hi>Burch,
Suayne</hi> and <hi>Rogers,</hi> to each a third part.</p>
               <p>Theſe lands were formerly granted out in Copie-holds to ſeuerall Tenants for terme of life, no greater Rent being reſerued or paid to the Crowne
at the time of the Grant, or for 60 yeares before, then 5 <abbr>l.</abbr> 9 <hi>
                     <abbr>s.</abbr> 
                     <hi>per annum,</hi>
                  </hi> as appeareth vpon record.</p>
               <p>A ſpeciall Act of Parliament did confirme this Grant, begun 43. <hi>Eliz.</hi> ended 19. Decemb. following, in which Act many prouiſions were made
for auoiding future queſtions, and fortiſying the titles of all who had or ſhould purchaſe lands of the ſaid Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> from the 25 yeare of her reigne
vntill the expiration of one whole yeare after the diſſoluing of that Seſſions, ended the 19 of Decemb. and for the confirming and eſtabliſhing the ſaid
lands to the purchaſers, againſt her Highneſſe, her heires and ſucceſſors for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sir Arthur Ingrams claime.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whitmore</hi> purchaſed <hi>Bridgewater Caſtrum, 8. Iacobi,</hi> euery particular parcell being expreſſed in the Grant, with the ſeuerall annuall rents thereof,
which in all made the iuſt yearely value they were purchaſed at; the lands in <hi>Heygraue</hi> being excepted in the ſaid Grant by expreſſe words.</p>
               <p>His Maieſtie about the ſame time granted the 5 <abbr>l.</abbr> 9 <hi>
                     <abbr>s.</abbr> 
                     <hi>per annum</hi>
                  </hi> the Fee-ſimple rent reſerued vpon the lands in <hi>Heygraue,</hi> to <hi>Eldred</hi> and <hi>Whitmore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From theſe two grants Sir <hi>Arthur Ingram</hi> makes his claime to <hi>Heygraue,</hi> only for that they bound and border one vpon the other: for in nine yeares
continuall ſuites by ſuch agents as were maintained by Sir <hi>Arthur Ingram</hi> againſt <hi>Rogers,</hi> he neuer ſhewed any euidence to make good his claime to
himſelfe, or euer recouered any part of the premiſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Rogers her grieuances.</head>
               <p>One <hi>Allen</hi> an agent for Sir <hi>Arthur Ingram</hi> with 6 or 7 irregular perſons in the night time did breake downe the doores and walls of <hi>Rogers</hi> tenement
in <hi>Heygraue</hi> called <hi>Ioyners,</hi> and wounding one <hi>Oſmond</hi> her ſeruant, threw him out of his peaceable poſſeſſion, to which being reſtored by a legal courſe,
<hi>Oſmonds</hi> death was ſought by poiſon, which not taking effect, <hi>Allens</hi> wife and <hi>Paul Allens</hi> ſeruant ſo wounded <hi>Oſmond,</hi> that ſhortly afterward he died.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Allen</hi> in the behalfe of Sir <hi>Arthur Ingram</hi> tooke the profits of <hi>loyners</hi> tenement for the ſpace of ſix yeares, felled downe the timber, defaced and rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
the Tenement, impounded <hi>Rogers</hi> cattell neare 30 ſeuerall times, which ſhe being inforced to repleavie, he neuer proceeds to triall, and almoſt 20
ſeuerall actions he and his combinants haue commenced againſt <hi>Rogers</hi> her ſeruants and Tenants cauſleſly and of meere vexation, arreſting and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning
them, and many times not declaring againſt them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rogers</hi> brought an eiectment in <hi>Oſmonds</hi> name againſt <hi>Vrſula Euens</hi> for <hi>Ioyners</hi> Tenement, to trie the title of the whole, which was followed againſt her
by Sir <hi>Arthur Ingram;</hi> whereupon a ſpeciall verdict was found at the Aſſiſes in <hi>Somerſetſhire,</hi> wherein the grant made 44 <hi>Eliz.</hi> to <hi>Beſt</hi> and <hi>Britton,</hi> the Act
of Parliament made for confirmation of the ſaid Grant as aforeſaid was likewiſe found, the lands were found to he in <hi>Heygraue,</hi> and to be pa<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the
ioynture of the Ladie <hi>Iane</hi> Queen of <hi>England,</hi> and the rent reſerued to be 5 <abbr>l.</abbr> 9 <hi>
                     <abbr>s.</abbr>
                  </hi> and no more at the time of the ſaid Graunt, and for <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> yeares before,
they alſo found <hi>Whitmores</hi> grant and the ſaid ſeuerall parcels therein, and the lands in <hi>Heygraue</hi> eſpecially excepted in the ſaid grant.</p>
               <p>To recouer the meane profits of <hi>Ioyners</hi> Tenement, <hi>Rogers</hi> commenced 3 actions againſt <hi>Allen, Parſons</hi> and <hi>Fenner</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Ingram;</hi> agents; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell
retained and the cauſes ready for hearing at the Aſſiſes, letters were directed from the Commons houſe of Parliament to the Iudges to ſtay the triall
vntill the laſt Parliament ended, for that Sir <hi>William Whitmore</hi> a Parliament man claimed title to the lands in queſtion, who neither then had nor euer
ſince challenged any intereſt therein.</p>
               <p>The Copie-hold Tenants (ſeduced by <hi>Allen</hi>) refuſe to pay <hi>Rogers</hi> their cuſtomary Rents, haue felled downe the timber, deſtroyed the woods, cut vp
the quickſet fences, and let fall the buildings on the premiſes, the ſpoiles whereof amount neare to the value of the lands; for which waſtes, forfeitures
and non paiments of the rents, <hi>Rogers</hi> two yeares ſince entred vpon two other tenements, but <hi>Allen</hi> (the Tenants being dead or fled) with other beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly
people entred vpon her poſſeſſions, and before the corne was ripe, reaped, ſpoiled and caried away the ſame, it being ſowne by Miſtris <hi>Rogers,</hi> to
her great loſſe and the publike hurt, affirming they did it for Sir <hi>Arthur Ingram.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Allen</hi> brought diuers actions againſt <hi>Rogers</hi> for theſe two Tenements, pretending Sir <hi>Arthur Ingram</hi> had good title thereto, one of them was tried
at the Kings Bench barre for both the Tenements, and a verdict thereupon given for <hi>Rogers,</hi> yet <hi>Allen</hi> perſcueres to take the profits, notwithſtanding
they were ſequeſtred in the Star-chamber by the Lord Keeper, and one of the Tenements ſetled vpon <hi>Rogers</hi> by a writ of Re-reſtitution out of the
Kings Bench.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Allen</hi> and others Sir <hi>Arthur Ingrams</hi> agents, beſides theſe and other continuall vexations, procured his Maieſties Iuſtices (abuſed by their falſe infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations)
to certifie againſt the ſaid Miſtris <hi>Rogers,</hi> the ſaid Iuſtices neither knowing her not vnderſtanding the cauſe aright.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Arthur Ingram</hi> failing by theſe indirect wayes, hath procured his Maieſties Attorney generall to exhibite an information of intruſion againſt <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,
Burch</hi> and <hi>Swayne</hi> in the Exchequer, intitling his Maieſtie to the lands in <hi>Heygraue,</hi> but proceeds onely againſt <hi>Rogers,</hi> which argues Sir <hi>Arthur
Ingram</hi> hath compounded with <hi>Burch</hi> and <hi>Swaine</hi> for their two parts, or at leaſt they are all combined to perſecute <hi>Rogers, Swaine</hi> hauing preferred a bil
in Chancerie againſt her for a third part of the profits of the Tenements recouered, and <hi>Burch</hi> threatneth to doe the like, the profits recouered not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting
to the hundreth part of what ſhe hath laid out in defence and recouery of the premiſes, of which they of right ought to allow an equal ſhare,
yet <hi>Rogers</hi> for 1500 <abbr>l</abbr> laid out, hath not had aboue 70 <abbr>l</abbr> of both of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The motiues why Rogers flies to this moſt honorable Court for reliefe.</head>
               <p>Theſe lands were ſold by Qu. <hi>Eliz.</hi> for paiment of her debts, maintenance of her warres, and the publike good, purchaſed at 30 yeares purchaſe, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in leaſe for liues, the Queene receiuing in hand for the lands paſſed in the ſame Grant 2320 <abbr>l.</abbr> 15 <hi>
                     <abbr>s.</abbr>. 11 <abbr>d.</abbr>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Grant was confirmed by Act of Parliament to the purchaſers, againſt the Queene, her heires and ſucceſſors, with the conſent of the Lords ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
and temporall, and Commons then aſſembled in this moſt honorable Houſe where your Honours now ſit.</p>
               <p>And both the Act and Grant found by ſpeciall verdict, and that often argued at the Kings Bench barre, where iudgement was giuen for <hi>Rogers</hi> as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid,
and another iudgement vpon a verdict was likewiſe giuen for her at the Kings Bench barre.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding all theſe former iniuſt moleſtations, wherein ſhe hath waſted her eſtate, and ſpent her childrens portions, to defend their rights a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the vſurping claime of greatneſſe, who calls all his, which lies neare his reach, Sir <hi>Arthur Ingram</hi> vowed to make her ſpend 500 <abbr>l</abbr> or the value of
the land: to effect which, he hath cauſed the information aforeſaid to be preferred againſt <hi>Rogers,</hi> contrary to the Act of Parliament formerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rogers</hi> is already ſo diſabled by theſe ſuites, as ſhe can no longer defend the goodneſſe of her cauſe againſt ſo ſtrong a perſecutor as Sir <hi>Arthur Ingram:</hi>
for although ſhe hath recouered in all her trials for the title, yet ſhe hath loſt her charges, for that Sir <hi>Arthur Ingram</hi> kept his perſon out of action, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying
beggers, non reſidents and fugitiues, who were conveyed away, and not to be found, or of whom nothing was to be had.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, <hi>Rogers</hi> humbly preſumes it imports not her alone, but all your Honours in generall, and moſt of you in particular, there being few or none
ſitting in this moſt honorable Houſe, but hold lands by the ſame or like grant. And if lands purchaſed vpon ſo valuable conſiderations, confirmed
by ſo high and honorable a Court, ſhalbe ſubiect to the cenſure of ſubordinate inferiour Courts; and aſſurances grounded vpon ſuch ſtrength, ſhall lie
open to euery nice point and cauill in law, found by litigious ſpirits, what eſtate vnder the Sunne can be firme or ſecure? For which reſpects, <hi>Rogers</hi>
humbly appeales to yours Honours, as the principall pillars that ſupports equitie and the publike good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The poore Widow and the Orphans prayer,</head>
               <p>That your Lordſhips will be humbly pleaſed (by decree of this moſt honorable Court) to ſettle <hi>Rogers</hi> her right and title to <hi>Heygraue</hi> and the lands
therein vpon her and her poſteritie (to whom of right it appertaines) according to her grant and the Act of Parliament aforeſaid, that ſhe may peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably
enioy them without further litigious ſuites, and they ſhall beſeech the Lord of all Lord to crowne you all with eternall glorie in the great Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
of Heauen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
